So, it's taken us a
ニューラルネットワークのアルゴリズムを
lot of videos to get through
見ていくのに
the neural network learning algorithm.
たくさんのビデオを費やしてきた。
In this video, what I'd like
このビデオでは、
to do is try to
全てのピースを一つに合わせて
put all the pieces together, to
全体的なサマリー、
give a overall summary or
あるいはより大きな
a bigger picture view, of how
鳥瞰図を提供したい、
all the pieces fit together and
全てのピースがどう組み合わさり
of the overall process of how
ニューラルネットワークを全体として
to implement a neural network learning algorithm.
どう実装したらいいのかについて。
When training a neural network, the
ニューラルネットワークをトレーニングする時は
first thing you need to do
最初にやらなくてはいけない事は
is pick some network architecture
なんらかのネットワークアーキテクチャを選ぶ事だ。
and by architecture I just
ここでアーキテクチャという言葉で
mean connectivity pattern between the neurons.
ニューロン同士の接続のパターンを意味している。
So, you know, we might choose
だから例えば
between say, a neural network
3つの入力ユニットに
with three input units
5つの隠れユニット、
and five hidden units and
そして4つの出力を
four output units versus one
選ぶかもしれないし、対して
of 3, 5 hidden, 5
3つ、5つの隠れ、5つの隠れ
hidden, 4 output and
4つの出力を選ぶかもしれないし、
here are 3, 5,
そしてこれは3で、 5, 5, 5ユニットが
5, 5 units in each
三つの隠れレイヤーに
of three hidden layers and four
あって、そして
open units, and so these
4つの出力ユニット、これを選ぶかもしれない。
choices of how many hidden
これらが幾つの隠れユニットと
units in each layer
幾つの隠れレイヤーを持つかの
and how many hidden layers, those
選択肢だ。
are architecture choices.
これらがアーキテクチャの選択肢だ。
So, how do you make these choices?
これらの選択肢をどうやって選ぶのか？
Well first, the number
まず、入力ユニットの総数は
of input units well that's pretty well defined.
かっちりと定義されている。
And once you decides on the fix
そして一旦固定されたフィーチャーの集まりxを
set of features x the
決定してしまえば、
number of input units will just be, you know, the
入力ユニットの数は、
dimension of your features x(i)
フィーチャーx(i)の次元によって
would be determined by that.
決定される。
And if you are doing multiclass
そしてもしマルチクラスの
classifications the number of
分類問題を扱っているなら、
output of this will be
出力の数は、
determined by the number
あなたの扱ってる分類問題の
of classes in your classification problem.
クラスの数によって決められる。
And just a reminder if you have
思い出してもらう為に触れておくと
a multiclass classification where y
マルチクラスの分類問題の時には、
takes on say values between
例えばyが1から10の間の数を取るとすると、
1 and 10, so that
つまり10個のとりうるクラスが
you have ten possible classes.
ある事になるが、
Then remember to right, your
その時は、覚えているだろうか、
output y as these were the vectors.
出力のyはこれらのベクトルとなるのだった。
So instead of clause one, you
つまりこれがクラス1で、
recode it as a vector
それをこのベクトルに再コーディングする。
like that, or for
二番目のクラスは
the second class you recode it as a vector like that.
こんなベクトルに再コーディングする。
So if one of these
だから、これらのうちの一つを
apples takes on
例として挙げると、
the fifth class, you know, y equals 5, then
5番目のクラスの場合、yイコール5の時は、
what you're showing to your neural
ニューラルネットワークにおいて見る事になるのは
network is not actually a value
y=5という値では無く、
of y equals 5, instead here
その代わりにここでは
at the upper layer which would
出力レイヤで、
have ten output units, you
この場合は10個の出力ユニットがあり、
will instead feed to the
そこに5番目に1があって
vector which you know
それ以外が0で埋まっているような
with one in the fifth
ベクトルを
position and a bunch of zeros down here.
食わせることになる。
So the choice of number
つまり入力ユニットと出力ユニットの
of input units and number of output units
総数の選択は
is maybe somewhat reasonably straightforward.
割とまっすぐ決まると思う。
And as for the number
そして隠れユニットと
of hidden units and the
隠れレイヤーの
number of hidden layers, a
数の選択については
reasonable default is to
もっとも普通の基本形は
use a single hidden layer
隠れレイヤは一層。
and so this type of
つまりこの左側に示したような
neural network shown on the left with
隠れレイヤ一つのニューラルネットワークが
just one hidden layer is probably the most common.
恐らくもっとも一般的な物と言える。
Or if you use more
そしてもし一つ以上の
than one hidden layer, again the
隠れレイヤを使うなら
reasonable default will be to
ここでも普通の基本形は
have the same number of
各レイヤの隠れユニットは
hidden units in every single layer.
同じ数にする、という物。
So here we have two
つまりここでは2つの
hidden layers and each
隠れレイヤがあり、
of these hidden layers have the
これらの隠れレイヤはそれぞれ
same number five of hidden
同じ隠れユニットの数である5つの隠れユニットを持ち、
units and here we have, you know,
こちらは見ての通り
three hidden layers and
3つの隠れレイヤがあり
each of them has the same
それらはそれぞれ、同じユニット数で
number, that is five hidden units.
それぞれ5つの隠れユニットがある。
Rather than doing this sort
だがこれらのネットワークアーキテクチャを使うまでもなく
of network architecture on the left would be a perfect ably reasonable default.
この左側のアーキテクチャでも十分に悪くないデフォルトの選択肢だ。
And as for the number
そして隠れユニットの
of hidden units - usually, the
数としては、通常は
more hidden units the better;
隠れユニットが多ければ多い程良いが
it's just that if you have
隠れユニットがたくさんあると
a lot of hidden units, it
計算量的には
can become more computationally expensive, but
高価になる。
very often, having more hidden units is a good thing.
だがしばしば、隠れユニットは多ければ多い程良い。
And usually the number of hidden
そして通常は、各レイヤーの
units in each layer will be maybe
隠れユニットの総数は
comparable to the dimension
だいたいxの次元と同じ程度、
of x, comparable to the
フィーチャーの総数と
number of features, or it could
同じ程度で、あるいは
be any where from same number
入力のフィーチャーの総数と
of hidden units of input features to
同じ程度から2倍とか3倍とか4倍程度の
maybe so that three or four times of that.
適当な数が良い。
So having the number of hidden units is comparable.
だから入力のフィーチャーと
You know, several times, or
同じ程度の数か、
some what bigger than the number
その数倍程度の数でも
of input features is often
やる価値のある事が
a useful thing to do So,
多い。
hopefully this gives you one
以上で、ニューラルネットワークの
reasonable set of default choices
アーキテクチャのデフォルトの選択として
for neural architecture and and
リーズナブルな選択肢を幾つか示せただろう。
if you follow these guidelines, you
そしてもしあなたがこれらのガイドラインに沿えば、
will probably get something that works
たぶんうまく機能する物が得られるだろう。
well, but in a
だがこの後の
later set of videos where
ビデオでは、
I will talk specifically about
アルゴリズムを
advice for how to apply
どう適用したらいいかについて
algorithms, I will actually
詳細な話をしていく。
say a lot more about how to choose a neural network architecture.
ニューラルネットワークのアーキテクチャをどうやって選んだらいいかについて、もっと多くの事を話していく。
Or actually have quite
また、実際に隠れユニットや
a lot I want to
隠れレイヤーの総数の
say later to make good choices
良い選び方について、などは
for the number of hidden units, the number of hidden layers, and so on.
たくさん話すつもりだ。
Next, here's what we
次に、ニューラルネットワークをトレーニングする為に
need to implement in order to
実装しなくてはいけない事は
trade in neural network, there are
これだ。
actually six steps that I
6つのステップがある。
have; I have four on this
このスライドでは4つ、
slide and two more steps
そして次のスライドに
on the next slide.
残り二つ。
First step is to set up the neural
最初のステップはニューラルネットワークを
network and to randomly
セットアップして、ウェイトの値を
initialize the values of the weights.
ランダムに初期化する。
And we usually initialize the
ウェイトの初期化は普通、
weights to small values near zero.
0付近の小さな値で初期化する。
Then we implement forward propagation
次にフォワードプロパゲーションを実装する、
so that we can input
入力をニューラルネットワークに入れて
any excellent neural network and
予測が計算出来るように。
compute h of x which is this
つまりhのxを計算し、
output vector of the y values.
この出力ベクトルのyの値を得る為に。
We then also implement code to
そして次にコスト関数である
compute this cost function j of theta.
Jのシータを計算するコードを実装する。
And next we implement
そして次にバックプロパゲーションを
back-prop, or the back-propagation
バックプロパゲーションアルゴリズムを実装する、
algorithm, to compute these
これらの偏微分の項を
partial derivatives terms, partial
計算する為に、、、
derivatives of j of theta
Jのシータの、パラメータによる
with respect to the parameters. Concretely, to implement back prop.
偏微分を計算する為に。 具体的には、バックプロバゲーションを実装するには、
Usually we will do that
普通はトレーニング手本に渡って
with a fore loop over the training examples.
for文を回して
Some of you may have heard of
あなたがたの中には
advanced, and frankly very
アドバンスドな、凄いアドバンスドな
advanced factorization methods where you
ベクトル化した方法を聞いた事がある人もいるかもしれない。
don't have a four-loop over
それはm個のトレーニング手本に渡っての
the m-training examples, that the
for文を回さない物だ。
first time you're implementing back prop
だが最初にバックプロパゲーションを
there should almost certainly the four
実装する時には、ほぼ確実にforループのある実装から
loop in your code,
始めるべきだろう。
where you're iterating over the examples,
そこでトレーニング手本に渡ってイテレーションを行い、
you know, x1, y1, then so
つまり、まずx1とy1に対して
you do forward prop and
最初の手本に対して
back prop on the first
フォワードプロパケーションとバックプロパゲーションを行い、
example, and then in
そして次に
the second iteration of the
forループの二回目のイテレーションで
four-loop, you do forward propagation
二番目の手本に対し
and back propagation on the second example, and so on.
フォワードプロパケーションとバックワードプロパゲーションを行う、などなど。
Until you get through the final example.
これを最後の手本に至るまで進める。
So there should be
つまり、少なくとも初めて実装する時には
a four-loop in your implementation
あなたのバックプロパゲーションの実装には
of back prop, at least the first time implementing it.
forループがあるはずだ。
And then there are frankly
そして簡単に言うと
somewhat complicated ways to do
なんか難しいやり方で
this without a four-loop, but
forループ無しのもある、という事。
I definitely do not recommend
だが私は心から
trying to do that much more
最初にバックプロパケーションを実装する時に
complicated version the first time you try to implement back prop.
その複雑なバージョンにチャレンジするのは、おすすめしない。
So concretely, we have a
さて、では具体的には、mトレーニング手本に渡る
four-loop over my m-training examples
for文があり、
and inside the four-loop we're
そしてfor文の中では、
going to perform fore prop
フォワードプロパゲートとバックワードプロパゲートを
and back prop using just this one example.
この一つの手本だけに対して行う。
And what that means is that
つまり、
we're going to take x(i), and
x(i)を持ってきて、
feed that to my input layer,
それを入力レイヤーに食わせて、
perform forward-prop, perform back-prop
フォワードプロパゲートとバックプロパゲートを実行する。
and that will if all of
するとニューラルネットワーク内の
these activations and all of
全てのレイヤーの全てのユニットの
these delta terms for all
アクティベーション全部と
of the layers of all my
デルタの項が全部
units in the neural
得られるので、
network then still
次に、まだforループの
inside this four-loop, let
内部だが、、、よし、
me draw some curly braces
中括弧を書こう、
just to show the scope with
forループのスコープを示す為に。
the four-loop, this is in
これはもちろんOctaveのコードなんだが、
octave code of course, but it's more a sequence Java
だがC++とかJavaのコードのシーケンスみたいな意味で
code, and a four-loop encompasses all this.
これはfor文をここ全体に拡張する。
We're going to compute those delta
我らはこれらのデルタの項を計算する訳だが
terms, which are is the formula that we gave earlier.
その式は以前に既に得ている。
Plus, you know, delta l plus one times
、、、足すことの デルタ l+1
a, l transpose of the code.
掛ける aのlの転置に、さらにコードが続く。
And then finally, outside the
そして最後に、これらのデルタ項が
having computed these delta
アキュームレーションの項が
terms, these accumulation terms, we
計算されたあとの外側では
would then have some other
さらに幾つかコードがあったあとで、
code and then that will
これらの偏微分の項の
allow us to compute these partial derivative terms.
計算が出来るようになる。
Right and these partial derivative
そしてこれらの偏微分の項は
terms have to take
正規化項のラムダも同様に
into account the regularization term lambda as well.
考慮に入れる必要がある。
And so, those formulas were given in the earlier video.
それらの式は前半のビデオで与えてあった。
So, how do you done that
だからそれを終えているなら、
you now hopefully have code to
これらの偏微分項を計算するコードを
compute these partial derivative terms.
既に手中に収めているはずだ。
Next is step five, what I
次はステップ5。
do is then use gradient
そこではグラディアントチェッキングを用いて
checking to compare these partial
計算した偏微分の項と
derivative terms that were computed. So, I've
比較する。
compared the versions computed using
つまりバックプロパケーションを用いて
back propagation versus the
計算したバージョンと、
partial derivatives computed using the numerical
微分を数値計算的に推計した偏微分の数値推計を
estimates as using numerical estimates of the derivatives.
比較する。
So, I do gradient checking to make
つまりグラディアントチェッキングを
sure that both of these give you very similar values.
これらの値が両方とも似通っている事を確認する為に使う。
Having done gradient checking just now reassures
グラディアントチェッキングで
us that our implementation of back
我らのバックプロパゲーションの実装が正しいと
propagation is correct, and is
確認した後には、
then very important that we disable
次のとても大事な事だが、グラディアントチェッキングを
gradient checking, because the gradient
disableする。何故なら
checking code is computationally very slow.
グラディアントチェッキングのコードは計算量的にとても遅いからだ。
And finally, we then
そして最後に、
use an optimization algorithm such
最急降下法なり
as gradient descent, or one of
アドバンスドな最適化アルゴリズムの
the advanced optimization methods such
L-BFGSとかConjugateグラディアントとか
as LB of GS, contract gradient has
fminuncで使われているアルゴリズムでもそれ以外のアルゴリズムでも
embodied into fminunc or other  optimization methods.
とにかく何かしらを用いて、、、
We use these together with
これらをバックプロパゲーションと共に
back propagation, so back
用いる、
propagation is the thing
つまりバックプロパゲーションが
that computes these partial derivatives for us.
これらの偏微分を我らに提供してくれる。
And so, we know how to
そしてコスト関数を
compute the cost function, we know
計算する方法を知っていて、
how to compute the partial derivatives using
バックプロパゲーションを用いて偏微分を計算する方法も
back propagation, so we
知っているので、
can use one of these optimization methods
これらの最適化手法のどれかを用いて
to try to minimize j of
Jのシータをパラメータシータの関数として
theta as a function of the parameters theta.
最小化する事を、試みる事が出来る。
And by the way, for
ところで、
neural networks, this cost function
ニューラルネットワークの場合、
j of theta is non-convex,
このコスト関数Jのシータは非凸関数、
or is not convex and so
言い換えると凸関数では無いので、
it can theoretically be susceptible
理論上はローカル最小に
to local minima, and in
陥りうるし、
fact algorithms like gradient descent and
実際、最急降下法や
the advance optimization methods can,
アドバンスドな最適化手法は、
in theory, get stuck in local
理論上はローカル最適に捕まってしまう事がありうる。
optima, but it turns out
だが実際には、
that in practice this is
通常はこれは
not usually a huge problem
そんなに大きな問題にならない。
and even though we can't guarantee
そしてこれらのアルゴリズムが
that these algorithms will find a
グローバル最小を探す、とは保証出来なくても、
global optimum, usually algorithms like
普通は最急降下法のようなアルゴリズムは
gradient descent will do a
このコスト関数Jのシータを
very good job minimizing this
小さくする、という仕事を
cost function j of
とてもうまくこなす。
theta and get a
そしてとても良い
very good local minimum, even
局所最小が得られる。
if it doesn't get to the global optimum.
それはグローバル最適では無いかもしれないが。
Finally, gradient descents for
最後に、ニューラルネットワークに対する
a neural network might still seem a little bit magical.
最急降下法は、まだこれでもちょっと魔法っぽく見えるかもしれない。
So, let me just show one
だからもう一つ
more figure to try to get
最急降下法がニューラルネットワークに
that intuition about what gradient descent for a neural network is doing.
何をしているかを示す図をお見せしたい。
This was actually similar to the
これは最急降下法を以前説明した時に用いた図に
figure that I was using earlier to explain gradient descent.
実は似た物だ。
So, we have some cost
あるコスト関数があり、
function, and we have
ニューラルネットワークの
a number of parameters in our neural network. Right
パラメータがある。
here I've just written down two of the parameter values.
ここではパラメータの値を二つ書いた。
In reality, of course, in
実際には、もちろん、ニューラルネットワークの場合、
the neural network, we can have lots of parameters with these.
もっとたくさんのパラメータを持ちうる。
Theta one, theta two--all of these are matrices, right?
シータ1もシータ2も行列だ。
So we can have very high dimensional
だからパラメータの次元はとても高次になりうる。
parameters but because of
だがプロットして
the limitations the source of
表示してみる側の
parts we can draw. I'm pretending
制約の為に、
that we have only two parameters in this neural network.
ニューラルネットワークに二つのパラメータしか無いかのように話をする。
Although obviously we have a lot more in practice.
実際にはもっとたくさんあるのは明らかだけど。
Now, this cost function j of
いま、このコスト関数Jのシータは
theta measures how well
そのニューラルネットワークが
the neural network fits the training data.
トレーニングデータにどれだけフィットしているかを測っている物だ。
So, if you take a point
つまりこんな点を
like this one, down here,
取るなら、この下側の、
that's a point where j
そこはJのシータがとても低い
of theta is pretty low,
点に対応し、
and so this corresponds to a setting of the parameters.
つまりこれは以下のようなシチュエーションのパラメータに対応する、
There's a setting of the parameters
つまりだいたいのトレーニング手本に対して
theta, where, you know, for most
仮説の出力が
of the training examples, the output
y(i)に極めて近くなるような
of my hypothesis, that may
そういうシチュエーションの
be pretty close to y(i)
パラメータに対応する。
and if this is
この条件が真の時が、
true than that's what causes my cost function to be pretty low.
コスト関数が極めて低い、という状態に対応する。
Whereas in contrast, if you were
他方、対照的に、
to take a value like that, a
こっちのような値を取る時には、
point like that corresponds to,
この点はトレーニング手本の大多数が、
where for many training examples,
ニューラルネットワークの出力が
the output of my neural
実際の値、
network is far from
実際の観測された値のy(i)から、
the actual value y(i)
大きく離れた値に
that was observed in the training set.
対応した点となる。
So points like this on the
つまりこの右側の点のような点は
line correspond to where the
トレーニングセットに対する
hypothesis, where the neural
仮説の出力、
network is outputting values
ニューラルネットワークの出力が、
on the training set that are
y(i)から遠く離れた値となる点に対応する。
far from y(i). So, it's not
だからそれはトレーニングセットには
fitting the training set well, whereas
あまり良くフィットしそうに無い。
points like this with low
他方このような点は、
values of the cost function corresponds
コスト関数の値が低いというのは
to where j of theta
Jのシータが低い所に対応しているので、
is low, and therefore corresponds
つまりはニューラルネットワークが
to where the neural network happens
ちょうど良く私のトレーニングセットに
to be fitting my training set
フィットする場所に対応する。
well, because I mean this is what's
何故ならこれこそがJのシータが小さくなる時に
needed to be true in order for j of theta to be small.
真である必要のある事だから。
So what gradient descent does is
だから最急降下法のやる事は、
we'll start from some random
なんらかの
initial point like that
ランダムな初期点から始めて、
one over there, and it will repeatedly go downhill.
たとえばこことか、そこから繰り返し丘を降りていく。
And so what back propagation is
つまりバックプロパゲーションが行うのは
doing is computing the direction
グラディアントの方向を
of the gradient, and what
計算して、
gradient descent is doing is
そして最急降下法がやる事は、
it's taking little steps downhill
一歩一歩ちょっとずつ丘を降りていき、
until hopefully it gets to,
期待するのは、そしてこの場合は実際にそうだが、
in this case, a pretty good local optimum.
かなり良いローカル最適に至るまで進む訳だ。
So, when you implement back
つまり、バックプロパゲーションを
propagation and use gradient
実装して、
descent or one of the
最急降下法やアドバンスドな最適化法の一つを
advanced optimization methods, this picture
使う時には、
sort of explains what the algorithm is doing.
この図はアルゴリズムが何をするかの、いくらかの説明となっている。
It's trying to find a value
それはニューラルネットワークの
of the parameters where the
出力する値が、
output values in the neural
トレーニングセットにおける観測値のy(i)に
network closely matches the
なるべく近いような
values of the y(i)'s
ニューラルネットのパラメータを
observed in your training set.
探す事を試みる。
So, hopefully this gives you
これで、あなたも
a better sense of how
ニューラルネットワークの
the many different pieces of
それぞれのピースが、どう組み合わさるのか
neural network learning fit together.
分かったんじゃないかな。
In case even after this video, in
でも、もしこのビデオが終わった後でも、
case you still feel like there
これらの様々なピースの中に
are, like, a lot of different pieces
いまいちどうもしっくり来ない物があったり、
and it's not entirely clear what
あるいはそれらのうちの幾つかが
some of them do or how all
完全にはっきりと分かったという訳で無くても、
of these pieces come together, that's actually okay.
あるいはこれらのピースがどうくっつくのか全部は分からなくても、実際は問題無い。
Neural network learning and back propagation is a complicated algorithm.
ニューラルネットワーク学習とバックプロパゲーションは複雑なアルゴリズムだ。
And even though I've seen
そして私ですら、
the math behind back propagation
バックプロパゲーションの背後にある数学を
for many years and I've used
長年見てきて、さらに自分で思うには
back propagation, I think very
バックプロパゲーションを
successfully, for many years, even
とても成功裡に何年も使い続けてきた私ですら、
today I still feel like I
こんにちでも、まだ時々
don't always have a great
バックプロパゲーションが正確に何やってるのかを
grasp of exactly what back propagation is doing sometimes.
いつもしっかりつかんでる、という訳では無いと感じる事がある。
And what the optimization process
そしてJのシータを最小化する最適化が
looks like of minimizing j if theta.
どう進んでいくかもしっかりとつかんでないと感じる事がある。
Much this is a much harder algorithm
これはより難しいアルゴリズムで、
to feel like I have a
これはしっかり分かるのが、、、
much less good handle on
これが正確に何をやっているのかを
exactly what this is doing
しっかりと把握するのが、
compared to say, linear regression or logistic regression.
線形回帰とかロジスティック回帰に比べて難しい。
Which were mathematically and conceptually
線形回帰などの方が数学的にも概念的にも
much simpler and much cleaner algorithms.
よりシンプルで、よりクリーンなアルゴリズムだ。
But so in case if you feel the
だがもしあなたが似たような物だ、と感じたとしても
same way, you know, that's actually perfectly
それはそれで完全にOKだ。
okay, but if you
だがバックプロパゲーションを
do implement back propagation, hopefully
実装してみれば、
what you find is that this
きっとこれがもっとも強力な
is one of the most powerful
学習アルゴリズムの一つだと
learning algorithms and if you
分かるだろう。
implement this algorithm, implement back propagation,
そしてもしこのアルゴリズム、バックプロパゲーションを
implement one of these optimization
これらの最適化手法の一つを実装すれば、
methods, you find that
バックプロパゲーションが
back propagation will be able
とても複雑で強力で
to fit very complex, powerful, non-linear
非線型な関数で
functions to your data,
あなたのデータにフィッティング出来て
and this is one of the
そしてこれがこんにちある中でも
most effective learning algorithms we have today.
最も効率的な学習アルゴリズムの一つである事が分かるだろう。